Recently, I flew over a crowd
مؤخرًا، طرت فوق حشد
of thousands of people in Brazil
من آلاف الناس في البرازيل
playing music by George Frideric Handel.
أعزف موسيقى لجورج فريدريك هاندل.
I also drove along the streets of Amsterdam,
أيضًا قمت بالسير على طول شوارع أمستردام،
again playing music by this same composer.
أعزف موسيقى لنفس المؤلف مرةً أخرى.
Let's take a look.
دعونا نلقي نظرةً.
(Music: George Frideric Handel, "Allegro." Performed by Daria van den Bercken.)
(موسيقى: جورج فريدريك هاندل، "أليجرو." أداء داريا فان دن بركين.)
(Video) Daria van den Bercken: I live there on the third floor.
(فيديو) داريا بركين: أعيش في الطابق الثالث
(In Dutch) I live there on the corner.
(بالهولندية) أعيش هناك على الزاوية.
I actually live there, around the corner.
أعيش هناك، بجوار الزاوية.
and you'd be really welcome.
وأنتم محل ترحاب بالطبع.
Man: (In Dutch) Does that sound like fun? Child: (In Dutch) Yes!
رجل: (بالهولندية) يبدو هذا صوت ممتع؟ طفل: (بالهولندية) نعم!
[(In Dutch) "Handel house concert"]
[(بالهولندية) "حفلة دارهاندل"]
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Daria van den Bercken: All this was a real
داريا فان دن بركين: كل هذا كان تجربةً
magical experience for hundreds of reasons.
سحريةً حقيقةً لمئات الأسباب.
Now you may ask, why have I done these things?
وقد تتساءلون الآن، لماذا قمت بتلك الأشياء؟
They're not really typical for a musician's
إنها لا تتوافق مع الحياة
day-to-day life.
العادية للموسيقي.
Well, I did it because I fell in love with the music
حسنًا، فعلتها لأني وقعت في الحب مع الموسيقى
and I wanted to share it with as many people
وأردت مشاركته مع أكبر قدر ممكن
as possible.
من الناس.
It started a couple of years ago.
بدأ هذا منذ عامين.
I was sitting at home on the couch with the flu
كنت مصابة بالأنفلونزا وأجلس في المنزل على الأريكة
and browsing the Internet a little,
وأتصفح الأنترنت قليلًا،
when I found out that Handel had written works
حيث اكتشفت أن هاندل قد كتب أعمال
for the keyboard.
للبيانو.
Well, I was surprised. I did not know this.
تفاجأت، لم أكن أعرف عنها.
So I downloaded the sheet music and started playing.
لذلك قمت بتحميل النوتة الموسيقية وبدأت العزف.
And what happened next was
وما حدث بعد ذلك كان
that I entered this state of pure,
دخولي هذه الحالة من الإعجاب
unprejudiced amazement.
الخالص غير المتحيز.
It was an experience
كانت تجربة
of being totally in awe of the music,
كونك في رهبة تامة من الموسيقى،
and I had not felt that in a long time.
ولم أكن قد شعرت بذلك من فترة طويلة.
It might be easier to relate to this when you hear it.
قد يكون اتصالك بهذا أسهل حين تسمعه.
The first piece that I played through
القطعة الأولى التي عزفتها
started like this.
كانت هذه.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Well this sounds very melancholic, doesn't it?
حسنًا، يبدو هذا حزينًا جدًا، أليس كذلك؟
And I turned the page and what came next
وقلبت الصفحة وما جاء بعدها
was this.
كان هذه.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Well, this sounds very energetic, doesn't it?
حسنًا، يبدو هذا مفعمًا بالحيوية، أليس كذلك؟
So within a couple of minutes,
ثم خلال دقيقتين،
and the piece isn't even finished yet,
والقطعة لم تكن انتهت بعد،
I experienced two very contrasting characters:
قمت بتجربة شخصيتين شديدتي التباين:
beautiful melancholy and sheer energy.
حزنًا جميلًا وطاقةً مطلقةً.
And I consider these two elements to be
وأعتبر هذين العنصرين
vital human expressions.
تعبيرات بشرية حيوية.
And the purity of the music makes you hear it
ونقاء الموسيقى يجعلك تستمع لها
very effectively.
على نحو فعال جدًا.
I've given a lot of children's concerts
قد قمت بأداء حفلات عديدة للأطفال
for children of seven and eight years old,
في سن السابعة والثامنة،
and whatever I play, whether it's Bach, Beethoven,
وأيًا كان ما أعزفه، سواء كان باخ، أو بيتهوفين،
even Stockhausen,
أو حتى شتوك هاوزين،
or some jazzy music,
أو بعض موسيقى الجاز،
they are open to hear it,
هم منفتحون للاستماع لها،
really willing to listen,
وعلى استعداد حقيقي للاستماع
and they are comfortable doing so.
وكانوا يقومون بذلك براحة.
And when classes come in
وحين تأتي فصول
with children who are just a few years older,
أطفال أعمارهم أكبر قليلًا فقط،
11, 12, I felt that I sometimes already had trouble
11، و12 شعرت أني أحيانًا أجد صعوبةً
in reaching them like that.
لأصل بهم لمثل ذلك.
The complexity of the music does become an issue,
تصبح تعقيدات الموسيقى قضية،
and actually the opinions of others —
وأراء الآخرين ـــ
parents, friends, media — they start to count.
الآباء، والأصدقاء، والإعلام ـــ تبدأ في العد.
But the young ones, they don't question
لكن الصغار، لا يسألون عن
their own opinion.
رأيهم الخاص.
They are in this constant state of wonder,
هم في هذه الحالة الدائمة من الإعجاب،
and I do firmly believe that we can keep listening
وأعتقد جازمةً أننا نستطيع الحفاظ على الاستماع
like these seven-year-old children,
مثل أطفال سن السابعة هؤلاء،
even when growing up.
حتى حين نكبر.
And that is why I have played
ولهذا قد عزفت
not only in the concert hall
ليس فقط في قاعات الحفلات
but also on the street, online, in the air:
لكن أيضًا في الشارع، والإنترنت، وفي الهواء:
to feel that state of wonder,
لأشعر بتلك الحالة من الإعجاب،
to truly listen,
لاستماع حقيقي،
and to listen without prejudice.
ولاستماع بدون تحيز.
And I would like to invite you
وأود أن أدعوكم
to do so now.
لتقوموا بذلك الآن.
(Music: George Frideric Handel, "Chaconne in G Major." Performed by Daria van den Bercken.)
(موسيقى: جورج فريدريك هاندل، "تشاكنو إن جي ماجور.")
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.